Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today we are, today's daf דף,
daf, we're a daf דף daf ahead, so
today's daf דף daf we're going to be doing 74.
Amar Rav אמר רב, Amar Rav, excuse me, amar Rav Nachman amar
Rabbah bar Bar Hana amar Rav אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רב. amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Bar Hana
amar Rav. Taba'at shel Avodat Kochavim טבעת של עבודת כוכבים, Taba'at shel
Avodat Kochavim, you've got a ring of Avoda Zara עבודה זרה Avoda
Zara that gets mixed up with, you know, it was a ring
that was basically worshipped or it was noy Avoda Zara נוי עבודה
זרה, noy Avoda Zara, it was put around an altar in order
to, you know, in order to beautify it, and it gets mixed
up with a thousand similar-looking rings. Okay, so shenitarav be-mea taba'ot שנתערב
במאה טבעות, shenitarav be-mea taba'ot, excuse me, a hundred. Ve-nafla ונפלה, Ve-nafla,
so that's not batel בטל, batel, okay. This is again something that's
not batel בטל. batel. Is it because Avoda Zara עבודה זרה Avoda
Zara is particularly weighty and never has bittul ביטול? bittul? Is it
because the ring is significant? Some combination of the two, we're not
going to worry about that exactly right now. But it's not batel
בטל. batel. Okay, ve-nafla achat mehen le-Yam HaGadol ונפלה אחת מהן לים
הגדול, ve-nafla achat mehen le-Yam HaGadol, and one of the rings fell
into the Mediterranean. Hutru kulan הותרו כולן, Hutru kulan, now you can
use all the rings because you can assume it's the bad one
that fell away. Okay, so and Avi's question is going to be
let's use, well, first of all, lechatchila לכתחילה lechatchila you're allowed to
throw it in? Presumably not. Okay, that's like ein mevatlin issur lechatchila
אין מבטלין איסור לכתחילה. ein mevatlin issur lechatchila. But the question that's
going to get is wait a minute, why doesn't something like this
then work on our mishna משנה? mishna? If every time we're going
to be strict and say no bittul ביטול, bittul, no bittul ביטול,
bittul, but then when something happens to one of them you can
blame it all on that one? This I think Michael asked this
the first day. Let's say that in our mishna משנה. mishna. So
we're going to get to that. Okay. Hutru kulan, de-amrinan hach denafal
hainu de-issura הותרו כולן דאמרינן הך דנפל היינו דאיסורא, Hutru kulan de-amrinan
hach denafal hainu de-issura, the one that fell, that's the one that,
let's assume that was the problematic one. Eitiv Rabbah le-Rav Nachman איתיביה
רבה לרב נחמן, Eitivah Rabbah le-Rav Nachman, so Rabbah challenged Rav Nachman.
Afilu achat be-ribo yamutu kulan אפילו
אחת בריבוא ימותו כולן, Afilu achat be-ribo yamutu kulan, our mishna משנה.
mishna. One in ten thousand, you have to let them all die.
Amai אמאי? Amai? Why? Nema de-issura mit נימא דאיסורא מית? Nema de-issura
mit? Eventually one of them is going to die first. So whichever
one happens to die first, let's say, oh, that was the shor
haniskal שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, and now we can bring the rest.
Okay, it's a pretty good question. Okay. Amar lei אמר ליה, Amar
lei, Rav de-amar ke-Rabbi Eliezer רב דאמר כרבי אליעזר. Rav de-amar ke-Rabbi
Eliezer. You're right. Not everybody holds of this idea, blame it all
on the one that got lost. Okay, that is that is the
position of Rabbi Eliezer רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer by the heads that
we spoke about a minute ago, right, by offering one of the
heads. So Rabbi Eliezer רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer has this idea, if
it happens to one thing, just blame it all on the one.
That is not the He's a tanna תנא, tanna, that's not the
opinion of the other rabbis, that's not the opinion of our mishna
משנה, mishna, this is a debated issue. Okay. So which Rabbi Eliezer
רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? That we quoted earlier. De-tnan Rabbi Eliezer omer
im karev harosh shel echad mehen yikrevu kol haroshim kulam דתנן רבי
אליעזר אומר אם קרב הראש של אחד מהן יקרבו כל הראשים כולם.
De-tnan Rabbi Eliezer omer im karev harosh shel echad mehen yikrevu kol
haroshim kulam. Okay, so that's a Rabbi Eliezer רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
position. Blame it on the one that got lost, blame it on
the one that you already did something to, blame it on the
one that died. Okay, and ve-inami ואינמי ve-inami for Rabbi Eliezer רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, once one of the cows died, you'd assume it
was the bad one. But that's a Rabbi Eliezer רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer position. Okay, now the gemara גמרא gemara says one minute, let's
go back now to this actual claim about the rings. Okay, we
explained why it's not like why our mishna משנה mishna doesn't assume
that because our mishna משנה mishna is a different approach, but within
this idea that you can blame it on the one that got
lost, ve-ha'amar Rabbi Elazar והאמר רבי אלעזר, ve-ha'amar Rabbi Elazar, and Rabbah
says now you can use all the rings if one of the
rings fell into the ocean. Ve-ha'amar Rabbi Elazar והאמר רבי אלעזר ve-ha'amar
Rabbi Elazar one minute, didn't Rabbi Elazar רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar say
lo hitar Rabbi Eliezer לא הותר רבי אליעזר, lo hitar Rabbi Eliezer,
Rabbi Elazar רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar the amora אמורא amora says Rabbi
Eliezer רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer the tanna תנא tanna when he said
it's okay if one of the heads was brought, he did not
permit ela shenayim shenayim אלא שנים שנים, ela shenayim shenayim, only if
you brought two heads at a time. Two heads are better than
one? Yes, from that point on. So one head got already brought,
you got a hundred you know sheep heads here, now you can
only bring two sheep heads at a time. Why? Because when you're
bringing two, one of them is definitely okay. So therefore you could
say, well, it's like a double sort of you know it's all
a fiction right but double Well first of all I'm going to
assume that the bad one was already brought, and number point and
number point number two I already of these two I'm bringing one
of them is definitely good so I'm going to presume if one
is good presume the other one is good also. Okay, so it's
like the you know the story about the what do you call
it the actuary that he would always like to be scared to
death like whenever he whenever he would be flying on a plane
because he because he had figured out the odds that there would
be a bomb on the plane so like you know so he
like and he just couldn't get it out of his head so
one day his friend sees him and he's on a plane flight
and he's totally calm, calm as a cucumber. He says what happened,
I thought you were scared to death about the odds of flying
on a plane with a bomb? He says yes he says but
now I brought the bomb. What do you think of the chance
that there are two bombs on the plane?
So okay so anyway alright so anyway so okay I got one
head is good, the other one's got to be definitely good. Anyway
anyway so he says so he has this double way to make
a fiction to allow us to assume it's okay. So if that's
true, if you're going according to Rabbi Eliezer רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
how can you put a ring on your finger? He would only
allow it when you're using two at a time. Okay, so and
and so this is not this case. So he says amar lei
אמר ליה amar lei he said back to him, ana nami tarti
ka-amina אנא נמי תרתי קאמינא ana nami tarti ka-amina or tarti tarti
ka-amina תרתי תרתי קאמינא, tarti tarti ka-amina, I also was talking about
two at a time. So what does that mean two at a
time? So Rashi רש"י Rashi says what it means is you sell
them two at a time because the problem of Avoda Zara עבודה
זרה Avoda Zara is getting benefit, okay, not you wear them. You
could say you wear them, you put two on a necklace on
a chain so you're always on two on your finger at the
same time, I don't know if you have to exactly. know exactly
simultaneously get it on your finger, but whatever. Anyway, you could say
that you're wearing them two at a time or רש"י Rashi says
you're selling them two at a time. Yes, that's the context I'm
talking about as well. Okay, so here we have a way not
like our משנה Mishnah that when we're going to be really strict
and say it's not בטל Batel that maybe we allow certain fictions
to allow you to assume that it got lost. Okay. אמר רב,
Amar Rav, says רב: Rav: טבעת של עבודת כוכבים, Taba'at shel Avodat
Kochavim, you have a ring of that was used for an idol
שנתערבה במאה טבעות She-nit'arvah be-me'ah taba'ot
mixed up to a hundred and there's no ביטול. Bittul. ופירשו ארבעים
למקום אחד ושישים למקום אחד U-pirshu arba'im le-makom echad ve-shishim le-makom echad
and the
and the pile got divided, forty went into split off into one
group, sixty into another group. פירשה אחת מארבעים Pirshah achat me-arba'im now
now you can't say now the funny thing here is I think
why the גמרא Gemara doesn't sort of discuss this in the context
of the earlier issue about the cows wandering off, right? It sort
of maybe presumed that whatever answer we've got there we've got here
that if just one ring separates we're not going to say כל
דפריש מרובא פריש. Kol de-parish me-ruba parish. Presumably for the same reason
we won't say it by the cow. Okay, so you got forty
here
and
you have sixty here. So you're not just going to say, "Oh
well, this is the, you know, let's assume that the problem is
in the majority," or, "Let's assume כל דפריש מרובא פריש," Kol de-parish
me-ruba parish, and let's assume all these forty are okay. You're not
allowed, right, you could say, "Why not just say this follows these
came from the majority?" You're not allowed to say that the same
way you're not allowed to say it with one cow that separated
off. So once stuff gets mixed up in this mixture, we're not
going to allow you to just take one and say that it's
okay. All right, although that's what that huge תוספות Tosafot in the
beginning was: when do we allow you to say כל דפריש מרובא
פריש? Kol de-parish me-ruba parish? Okay, because sometimes we actually do say
it. But we're not going to let you to say it here.
They were all part of the initial mixture and all these forty,
even though they're the minority, all these forty remain forbidden. Okay fine.
But now, so you've got them into forty and sixty.
Now,
פירשה אחת מארבעים אינה אוסרת אחת משישים אוסרת. Pirshah achat me-arba'im eina
oseret achat mi-shishim oseret. So now you've got another big pile of
rings over here, okay, you've got all your rings here, okay, another
hundred rings, different from the initial, or another thousand rings, whatever it
is, doesn't matter. Ten thousand. Different from the ring. If one of
these rings comes here, goes here, okay, then we can say this
pile remains okay. Because even though when it separates off from the
initial pile, okay, we're not going to say כל דפריש מרובא פריש,
Kol de-parish me-ruba parish, we're going to say it was all part
of the initial mixture and the rabbis said that whole initial mixture
is forbidden. When one thing comes from here and falls into a
second mixture, then we're essentially going to say, well, most likely this
since since this was the minority, it was split in half and
this was the minority, most likely the problematic ring remained here.
Okay, so so because this
remains the
problematic pile, something from here
that goes into another mixture is going to be a problem. Logically
you could say that. But that's but again, the rabbis say we
don't let you say כל דפריש, Kol de-parish, and specifically by the
case of עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, what they say is even if
one ring of the mixture falls into mixture two and like one
ring of mixture two falls into mixture three, it's going to continuously
make the next mixture forbidden. That's specifically what they say here. So
yes, logically you should say even if one ring falls comes from
here we should assume it's okay and the next mixture remains okay.
But no, the classic statement about this ring of עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah is, right, you've got one ring in here that's bad, okay,
right, and all the rest are good, okay, and one falls into
pile two and from pile two into pile three, we basically say
they're all not good. We don't say כל דפריש מרובא פריש. Kol
de-parish me-ruba parish. That's the classic thing we say by עבודה זרה.
Avodah Zarah. Okay, so there when it comes from here into pile
two, that's the classic thing we say: when something from the bad
mixture falls into another pile, it's going to remain a problem. But
we're going to be lenient if this pile itself got split into
two. And if the pile itself got split into two, then we're
prepared to say that when something from the smaller pile falls in,
we're going to assume that this remains the base the fundamentally problematic
pile because this had the majority, okay, so there's more likely the
problematic ring was here. So because this remains the problematic pile, something
from here that goes into another mixture is going to be a
problem. This is not it's not totally okay. Okay, this remains forbidden
because it came from the larger group, but it's going to be
less likely to be problematic to the point that when it falls
into here we're going to say most likely it wasn't in here.
So isn't that kind of a fiction?
What? Of course it's a fiction, but the whole fact that we
said even one in a hundred isn't בטל batel is a fiction,
it's a Rabbinic rule. We're making up the rules, okay? So the
same way we don't allow ביטול, bitul, we can allow cases where
ביטול bitul will work, okay? Like why did we just not even
allow just just this? Why don't we say כל דפריש מרובא פריש,
kol d'parish me-rubba parish, right? So no, normally by עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah we say even one and one and one, we don't apply
the rules of כל דפריש. kol d'parish. And therefore here it remains
forbidden. But when that initial pile is split into two, we're not
so prepared to say, oh this now is the okay pile, because
that again is like part of the original mixture, but we are
prepared to say that if something from it falls somewhere else, we're
going to assume that it was an okay thing that fell in.
Okay? So that's what he says. Let's take a look. פירש אחת
מארבעים, Perish achas m'arbayim, okay, שנתערבו בשישים במקום אחד, shenitzrevu b'shishim b'makom
echad, פירש אחת מארבעים אינו אוסרת, perish achas m'arbayim eino oseres, אחת
משישים אוסרת. achas mi-shishim oseret. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, מאי שנא אחת מארבעים דלא?
mai shna achas m'arbayim d'lo?
Why is when it comes from the forty pile it's not a
problem? דאמרינן איסורא ברובא איתא, d'amrinan issura b'rubba isa,
the prohibited remains in the majority, אחת משישים נמי אמרינן איסורא ברובא
איתא. achas mi-shishim nami amrinan issura b'rubba isa.
So I don't get it. So say here too, even it's only
one, but but let's assume that, you know, that the forbidden one
remains with the majority and this one ring is actually okay.
The reverse of מרובא פריש me-rubba parish as a different way of
saying.
Right, it's the same point, but it's saying it in a different
way. Rather than saying this came from the majority and the majority
here is okay, let's say that the bad one remained with the
majority. Okay, so, אלא אם פירשו ארבעים כולם למקום אחד, ela im
pirshu arbayim kulam l'makom echad, אין אוסרות, ein oserot, שישים למקום אחד
אוסרות. shishim l'makom echad oserot.
Okay,
so it says, you know what, you're right. What it's really saying
is is that if all of these forty go off separate, and
maybe they all get mixed up somewhere else, they're all then then
that's going to be okay, whereas if all these sixty get separate,
then this pile of sixty and then that, you know, this pile
of sixty remains forbidden. So this גמרא Gemara seems to be actually
saying something quite surprising. It seems to actually be saying, you know
what, if one of them separated it actually would be okay, you
know, which is quite surprising. It actually actually, you know what it
says, you're right. We can say כל דפריש מרובא פריש kol d'parish
me-rubba parish and at least pile number two is okay. So what
did we need to say when we said the difference of the
sixty and the forty? The difference of the sixty and the forty
we were just saying that that this pile as a whole fell
in somewhere else, again, if it remained part of the original pile
we just split the pile in two it's a problem. But if
the whole pile as a whole got mixed into something, that other
thing is going to be okay because we can say the רוב
rov remained here. Or if this pile as a whole got mixed
into something, then it's going to remain a problem. But here the
גמרא Gemara although we normally say, you know, one and one and
one remains a problem, here the גמרא Gemara saying actually if we
were based it on the principle of כל דפריש, kol d'parish, logically
even if it came from the sixty it should be okay. All
right, so let's take a look.
Okay, one minute.
I'm just checking רש"י. Rashi. Yes. Okay, so so that's what it's
saying, okay. אחת משישים נמי אמרינן איסורא ברובא איתא, achas mi-shishim nami
amrinan issura b'rubba isa, אלא אף על פי ד... ela af al
pi de... כי אמריתה קמיה דשמואל, Ki amrisa kamin d'Shmuel, when I
said this to שמואל, Shmuel, אמר לי, amar lei, אמר לי, amar
li, הנח לעבודת כוכבים שספיקה וספק ספיקה אסורה עד סוף העולם. hanach
l'avodas kochavim she-sfeika v'sfek sfeika assura ad sof ha-olam. So שמואל Shmuel
says actually that's not true, meaning you asked, you know, you asked
why when one fell in why don't we just say, you know,
it all came from the רוב? rov? So שמואל Shmuel says uh-uh,
by עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah we don't play those games. We don't
play כל דפריש, kol d'parish, I don't agree to this, if one
came from here we would say we don't say you go by
רוב, rov, we would say it's forbidden, not only that if the
forty got mixed up with somewhere else we would not say oh
it got left here and those forty are all okay even if
they got mixed up in another pile, no matter how many additional
mixtures and additional doubts are going to pile onto one another, okay,
by עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
we're always going to say it always remains forbidden. That's the stringency
of עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, right? And that's what he was asking,
and that's normally what we say, even if one comes from one
pile, one comes from the next pile, it's all going to remain
forbidden. Okay,
so okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, עד
סוף העולם. ad sof ha-olam. מיתיבי, Meisvei, I'll ask you this principle
that we say it always remains forbidden. Here we've got a ברייתא,
Braita, the ברייתא Braita says ספק עבודת כוכבים אסורה וספק ספיקה מותרת,
safek avodas kochavim assura v'sfek sfeika muteres, the first ספיקה sfeika is
forbidden but a ספק ספיקה sfek sfeika is permissible. כיצד, Keitzad, what's
the case? כוס של עבודת כוכבים שנפל לאוצר מלא כוסות, Kos shel
avodas kochavim shenafal l'otzar malei kosot, one goblet of עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah fell into a warehouse filled with goblets. Okay, כולם אסורין, kulam
asurin, they're all forbidden. פירש אחד מהן לריבוא ומריבוא לריבוא. peirash echad
mehen leribo umeribo leribo. So this is pile number three already, okay?
One cup comes into ten thousand, from ten thousand to ten thousand,
now the question, so then it says at least by pile three
it says מותרין, mutarin, they're permissible. Now that's at least a ספק
ספק ספיקא, sfek sfek sfeka, right? I mean, it goes here, right,
you know, and then from here anyway, but at least pile number
three is okay.
And תוספות Tosfos says it could be even pile number two is
okay. The reason we spoke about pile number three was because there's
a strict opinion that says even pile three is forbidden. But the
one that says pile three is okay might go so far to
even say pile two is okay. Okay, but anyway, so here's a
position that actually by עבודה זרה Avoda Zara it works like other
things. And if it falls from that mixture, the next pile or
at least the third pile might be okay. Alright, so exactly this
question, do we say here when one out of the sixty falls
in, it's going to be okay or not? Are we normally willing
to do like כל דפריש מרובא פריש, kol deparish meruba parish, you
know, at least by pile number two? So שמואל Shmuel says no,
we don't do any of this stuff, it's עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara,
and here we have a ברייתא Braita that says at least by
the goblets that at least pile three we are going to be
prepared to say it.
So רב, Rav, this would be even more stringent in רב's Rav
day?
Yeah, well no, well depends if you...
unclear. Anyway, unclear, but anyway, but the גמרא Gemara says like this:
Okay, תנאי היא. Tannai hi. So you know what, you're right, that
question of are you prepared to apply these types of rules by
עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, where שמואל Shmuel said no and this ברייתא
Braita said yes, it's actually a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא, Detanya,
we learned in a ברייתא, Braita, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer,
רימוני בדן, Rimonei Badan, our famous pomegranates of בדן Badan that are
not בטל. batel. Okay, and this is now by ערלה, orla, it
isn't even by עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. אוסרין בכל שהן, Osrin bechol
shehen, even one of them in many is forbidden because it's significant
and not בטל. batel. כיצד? Keitzad? What's the example of that? נפל
אחד מהן לתוך ריבוא, Nafal echad mehen letoch ribo, one pomegranate of
ערלה orla fell into a thousand pomegranates, ומריבוא לריבוא, umeribo leribo, and
from there thousand, technically ten thousand, to another, אסורים, asurim, that's forbidden.
So this now he's saying this not even by עבודה זרה. Avoda
Zara. Right, normally we assume this idea that one and then one
into pile two and from pile two into pile three it all
remains forbidden, that's an עבודה זרה Avoda Zara idea. Here he's saying
it even by ערלה. orla. Okay, you've got a pomegranate of ערלה
orla mixed up with these others, it's not בטל. batel. One from
pile one into pile two, one from pile two into pile three,
they're all going to be forbidden. So he's very strict even by
ערלה orla that it keeps making the next piles forbidden. Alright, that
is the first opinion of the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. רבי שמעון
בן יהודה אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda omer, I'm sorry, that's the
opinion of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Shimon. So רבי
שמעון's Rabbi Shimon son now, רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, said in the
name of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, siding with his father's colleague against
his father. Okay, how's that permissible from כיבוד אב ואם? Kibbud Av
v'Eim? I'll let you worry about that. לריבוא אסורין, Leribo asurin, the
into the first mixture from this from you know into pile number
two it's
forbidden, לריבוא אסורין ומריבוא לשלש ומשלש למקום אחר מותר. leribo asurin umeribo
leshalosh umeshalosh lemakom acher mutar. But by the time you get to
pile number three, even if there's just going to be three of
them, so it's just going to be a simple רוב. rov. Now
it sounds like one from here falls into three, so it's actually
there's going to be a total of four. The גמרא Gemara is
going to ask why isn't it enough that it falls into a
pile of two so there's a majority. Okay, but he's basically saying
I agree with you that pile number two is going to be
a problem. Again, logically even pile number two shouldn't be a problem,
we should say כל דפריש מרובא פריש, kol deparish meruba parish, right?
Even if one falls in, likely it came from the majority. Okay,
but he's saying fine, pile number two is a problem for whatever
reason, but at least by pile number three even a small majority
is going to be okay. Alright, so this is by ערלה. orla.
So by
ערלה orla you've got רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda saying never
and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon saying pile three. Okay, now and now
שמואל Shmuel says by עבודה זרה Avoda Zara never,
and we have a ברייתא Braita that says by עבודה זרה, Avoda
Zara, right? Remember the ברייתא Braita says from a ריבוא ribo to
a ריבוא ribo whatever says by pile three it's okay. Alright, so
that's what we've got. So now we're basically going to say: How
שמואל Shmuel said עבודה זרה Avoda Zara is never בטל? batel? The
ברייתא Braita said this case of the goblets is בטל batel by
pile three. So how could שמואל Shmuel argue on the ברייתא? Braita?
So it says שמואל Shmuel is going basically like רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says even by ערלה orla it's never
בטל. batel. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: שמואל
דאמר כמאן? Shmuel de'amar keman? So one minute, who is שמואל Shmuel
going like? אי כרבי יהודה, Ei keRabbi Yehuda, you'll say he's going
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says by
ערלה orla by the pomegranates it's never בטל. batel. But אפילו בשאר
איסורין אסר, afilu beshear issurin assar, then why did שמואל Shmuel say
by עבודה זרה Avoda Zara it's never בטל? batel? רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says this applies by all איסורין, issurin, it's not unique to
עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, right, people got that?
אי כרבי שמעון, Ei k'Rabbi Shimon, if it's like Rabbi Shimon, אפילו
בעבודת כוכבים נמי שרי, afilu ba'avodat kochavim nami sharei, that Rabbi Shimon
didn't say anything by עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, Rabbi Shimon said by
ערלה Orlah pile three is okay. The Gemara's going to assume that
Rabbi Shimon since he didn't say anything different about עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah would also say by עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah pile three is
okay. So who is he going like? Rabbi Shimon says it's all
okay and Rabbi Yehuda says it's all not good. Shmuel splits his
vote between עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and other things. Okay, so the
Gemara says וכי תימא שאני ליה לרבי שמעון עבודת כוכבים לשאר איסורים,
vechi teima shani lei l'Rabbi Shimon avodat kochavim lishar issurim, maybe Rabbi
Shimon who says by ערלה Orlah pile three is okay would say
that's only by ערלה. Orlah. Maybe he would say by עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah it's not good. אלא הא דתניא, Ela ha d'tanya, that
which we taught in a Baraita, ספק עבודת כוכבים אסורה וספק ספיקא
מותרת, safek avodat kochavim assura v'safek sefeika muteret, מאן? man? לא רבי
יהודה ולא רבי שמעון. Lo Rabbi Yehuda v'lo Rabbi Shimon. But wait,
we've got a Baraita that says
that the, you know, the double doubt of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
is going to be okay. We've got this Baraita, okay, that says
that by pile three it's okay. And why is that not Rabbi
Shimon? Hold on a minute.
One minute. ולשאר איסורים וכי תימא שאני ליה לרבי שמעון עבודת כוכבים
לשאר איסורים, v'lishar issurim vechi teima shani lei l'Rabbi Shimon avodat kochavim
lishar issurim, that by avodah, oh, that by avodah, right. Because then
it's going to be yes, yes, yes. Okay. So it says like
this: Who is, Shmuel says never. Who is Shmuel going like? Okay?
Shmuel says, everybody with me here, Shmuel says עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah,
specifically עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah says Shmuel is never בטל. batel. Okay?
So who is Shmuel going like? If Shmuel is going like Rabbi
Yehuda, then Rabbi Yehuda says it's not just עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah,
nothing is ever בטל, batel, no matter how many piles. If he's
going like Rabbi Shimon, so maybe he would say, ah, Rabbi Shimon
says ערלה Orlah is בטל batel by pile three, but I'm going
to say Rabbi Shimon would agree with me that by עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah it's not בטל, batel, even by pile three. But you've
got a problem, okay? Because the Baraita says it is בטל batel
by pile three. So this Baraita isn't going like anybody, right? Because
Rabbi Yehuda says it's never בטל batel and you're saying that Rabbi
Shimon would say that it's also not בטל batel in עבודה זרה.
Avodah Zarah. Okay, so we've got a problem because the Baraita says
that by עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah it is בטל. batel. So who
are you going like, Shmuel? You can't, that's against the Baraita. You
can't say Rabbi Yehuda because Rabbi Yehuda says it by other things,
and you can't say Rabbi Shimon because then you're leaving the Baraita
to go like no one. So the Gemara says:
לא רבי יהודה ולא רבי שמעון. לעולם רבי שמעון. Lo Rabbi Yehuda
v'lo Rabbi Shimon. L'olam Rabbi Shimon. Fine, so you're right. Okay. The
Baraita that says pile three by עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is Rabbi
Shimon that says pile three is okay and basically it says עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah is no different than anything else. Okay, so if
Rabbi Shimon is the one that says
pile
three by ערלה, Orlah, he's the author of the Baraita that says
pile three by עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah.
So who's Shmuel going like? Because Shmuel says never, which is similar
to Rabbi Yehuda's never by ערלה, Orlah, but Shmuel limits it to
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So who's he going like? So the Gemara
says: ושמואל
סבר לה כרבי יהודה בחדא ופליג עליה בחדא. V'Shmuel savar lah k'Rabbi
Yehuda b'chada u'palig alei b'chada. He basically embraces Rabbi Yehuda half the
way. Okay, yes, there's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. The debate of
תנאים Tannaim does not single out עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. In the
debate of תנאים, Tannaim, either you're a Rabbi Yehuda person who says,
you know, whenever something isn't בטל, batel, it doesn't matter how many
piles, it's never בטל batel even one to, you know, for one
pile to the next to the next to the next. Or you're
a Rabbi Shimon person that says by at least by pile three
it's בטל. batel. In the תנאים, Tannaim, עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah isn't
different. Shmuel says, I'm going to split my vote. And when it
comes to עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah I'm going to vote like Rabbi
Yehuda and say it's never בטל, batel, and when it comes to
other things I'm going to vote like Rabbi Shimon and say that
at least by the time you get to pile three it is
בטל. batel.
So the conclusion is Shmuel is not following any particular תנא Tanna
for all cases.
Right, exactly, he splits his vote. אמר מר, Amar Mar, now let's
go back and look at that debate by the
ערלה. Orlah. מעריבה לשלש ומשלש למקום אחר מותר. Me'ariva l'shalosh u'mishalosh l'makom
acher mutar. So it gets mixed up in pile one. Okay? That's
going to remain forbidden, this pomegranate. And then to pile two with
even if there's just three there, it's going to be permissible because
that's at least your second pile, or your third pile if you
count the original one, and then it is going to be בטל.
batel. So the Gemara says: one minute. משמע שלשה, Mashma shelosha, why
do we have to have three in that pile? דאיכא רובא, D'ika
ruba, you want it to have the majority. So שנים נמי איכא
רובא. shenayim nami ika ruba. So why didn't it just say it
fell into a pile of two? Right? Why is three better than
two? If you want to go by a simple majority, okay, you
should have just said it fell into a pile of two. So
the Gemara says: no. מאי ג' דקתני תרתי והוא. Mai gimmel d'katani
tarti v'hu. Now when it says it fell into a pile of
three, it means at the end there's three. It means it fell
into a pile that there were two and now there are three.
Okay? So that's why the second pile has a sim—or the third
pile has a simple majority. ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it eima, if you want
I can say, סבר לה כרבי אליעזר. savar lah k'Rabbi Eliezer. He
holds like
Rabbi
Eliezer. So רש''י Rashi has two ways of reading it. I'm going
to read it the simple way. Remember רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
that when you do when you allow something some something gets lost
you're allowed to benefit from it but
only two at a time, right? So that was when one of
them got lost. Here nothing got lost, it's just a second, a
third pile of ביטול. bittel. But maybe רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would
say his principle here too. So when are we going to allow
it from this pile? We're only going to allow it if you
benefit from it two at a time, like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
because then one of them is always okay. So that's why we
wanted to say three, so I can take two and then I
can take the next two, okay, whereas if I just had that's
why I want to say you have a total of four. But
if you only had a total of three, I guess you could
benefit from all three at a time, but you couldn't do it
two and then two and then two. All right, whatever. Either way,
we got the idea. This is, when you say something is בטל,
battel, the גמרא Gemara noticed does not go back to ask its
basic question. Let's just say כל דפריש מרובא פריש, kol deparish meruba
parish, which is what it asked by the animals. Presumably it feels
whatever answer it gave by the cows where afraid you're going to
take from it בקבוע bikavuah would be a general rule. And when
something gets mixed up and it's not בטל, battel, then the question
is, we do not say just take one and say מרובא פריש.
meruba parish. But what if that one fell into another pile? Will
the second pile be okay? What if it fell into a third
pile? Will the third pile be okay? So here what we've said
is, there are some that say that yes, at least pile three
is okay. תוספות Tosafos has a discussion that it could be even
pile two is okay. Okay, maybe when you take one by itself
you don't say מרובא פריש, meruba parish, but when it actually gets
mixed up into a second mixture maybe you're allowed to say it's
okay. Okay, but certainly there's opinions that say pile three is okay.
There's opinions that say it's never okay, no matter even at pile
three, pile four, whatever. And then there's שמואל Shmuel who splits the
vote between עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and other things. Okay. All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, said ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, חבית
של תרומה שנתערבה במאה חביות. chavis shel trumah shenisarva be'me'ah chaviol. You've
got a barrel of תרומה, trumah, and normally תרומה trumah is בטל
battel in a hundred. But remember, one of the things that's not
בטל battel the same way it's the בדן Badan pomegranates, one of
the things that's not בטל battel are sealed barrels of wine. You
might remember that. That was on our list of the six or
seven things that are not בטל. battel. So you've got this one
sealed barrel of תרומה trumah wine that gets mixed up with these
other barrels. So the answer is, what's the answer? Not בטל. battel.
Okay. Now, ונפחתה, venifta, okay, במאה חביות, be'me'ah chaviol, ונפלה אחת מהן
לים המלח. venafala achas mehen leyam hamelach. And one of them fell
into the into the Mediterranean. הותרו כולן, hutru kulan, they're all permissible.
I'm sorry, Dead Sea, right. ים המלח, Yam Hamelach, you're floating down
the Dead Sea, right. Before it was ים הגדול. Yam Hagadol. If
you're floating in the Dead Sea, I understand that. דאמרינן האי נפלה
דאיסורא נפלה. de'amrinan hai nafalah de'isura nafalah. This is like the position
of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer with if you brought one of the
heads, or it's like the רבא Rava who sided with it רבא
Rava who sided with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and said if one
of the rings fell into the Mediterranean. Okay. So now, although we
said this is a debate of אמוראים, Amoraim, it's not surprising, right,
that the גמרא, Gemara, if you make something so forbidden that there's
going to be some pressure to find a way to make it
permissible. Okay. So even though the גמרא Gemara said it's a debate
of אמוראים, Amoraim, we seem to be siding with this idea that
if something happens to one of them you can assume that one
was the problematic one. Okay. So the same way we said it
by the heads and the rings, we're saying it now by this
barrel. Okay. ואיצטריך דרב נחמן ואיצטריך דריש לקיש. ve'itztarich de'Rav Nachman ve'itztarich
de'Reish Lakish. You need רב נחמן Rav Nachman saying it by the
case of I think רב נחמן Rav Nachman was the one who
said it by the case of the rings,
yes, רב נחמן Rav Nachman said it by the rings in the
name of רב, Rav, and you need the teaching of ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish by the case of barrels. דאי מרב נחמן, de'ee mi'Rav
Nachman, had you just had רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, הוה אמינא hava
amina I would have thought הני מילי עבודה כוכבים. hani milei avodah
kochavim. Maybe that's by idolatry, the case of the rings, דאין להם
מתירין. de'ein lahem matirin. Normally you'd say idolatry is stricter. We just
got through saying even, you know, שמואל Shmuel says it's always forbidden
no matter how many piles. But there's an argument to say we're
going to give you more of a way to get out of
it by עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Because by עבודה זרה avodah zarah
if it's all forbidden you're stuck, there's no way it could ever
you could ever get access to it. So because it becomes totally
off limits, we might give you more of a possible out. So
maybe this idea that we'll blame it on the one that fell
into the sea, we would only say that by עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. אבל תרומה דיש לה מתירין, aval trumah de'yesh lah matirin, תרומה
trumah can become permissible. Now it doesn't literally mean can become permissible,
but it means there's a way to there's a way to benefit
from תרומה. trumah. How would you benefit from תרומה? trumah? What would
you do with תרומה? trumah? If you got all your wine mixed
up and there was תרומה trumah in it? It wouldn't be unusable,
who could use it?
A כהן. Kohen. Okay. So since תרומה trumah is not completely unusable,
maybe we didn't allow you to use this fiction. Okay. Lo, I
would say you can't use this fiction by תרומה. trumah. That's why
we had to tell it by תרומה trumah as well, by the
barrel of תרומה. trumah. ואי מריש לקיש, ve'ee mi'Reish Lakish, if it
was ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, הוה אמינא hava amina חבית דמינכר נפילתה.
chavis de'minchar nefilasah. Maybe by a barrel where a whole barrel from
a mix of barrels falls in, it's clear that a barrel is
missing. Okay. And since it's clear that a barrel missing, and it
allows us more psychologically to be okay with the fact that we're
going to say that there's no תרומה Terumah here, because we all
look at our row of barrels and we see the missing barrel,
as it were. Okay, so that allows it more to work at
a psychological level and us to blame it on the missing one,
because it's obvious one is missing. אבל טבעת לא מינכרא נפילתה, Aval
taba'at lo minchara nefilatah, but a ring, nobody sees when a ring
falls into the ocean, and nobody sees that a ring is missing.
So therefore the event of it falling in the ocean isn't a
big deal, right? I guess it's also true, a barrel makes a
splash. So in one case, the event of it falling is a
big deal, and its absence is noticed, and therefore it's easier to
say, oh, we're going to blame it on that barrel. But the
ring, which is less so, I would say לא, Lo, maybe you
can't blame it on the ring. It's so interesting here how the
issue because it is a fiction, the ability to blame it has
something to do with how psychologically, you know, we are going to
sort of pay attention to it. Anyway, the intersection of this with
like anthropology, psychology, anyway, לא. Lo. So therefore it comes down with
צריכי, Tzrichi, in both cases we're allowed to blame it on the
thing that fell away. So here we have that even though it's
a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, and even though you could distinguish cases,
we're going to be, you know, expanding this idea that if something
fell, you can blame it on what fell. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אבל תאנה, Aval te'ena,
so now, לא. Lo. אמר רבא לא היא דריש לקיש אלא כחבית
דמינכרא נפילתה, Amar Rava lo hi d'Reish Lakish ela ke-chavit d'minchara nefilatah,
so exactly that thing that we pushed against, now we're going to
actually suggest exactly limiting it that way. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish only
permitted it by a barrel that you see when it plops into
the ocean. אבל תאנה לא, Aval te'ena lo, if you had a
fig that was forbidden that mixed up into other figs, and then
one fig fell into the ocean, you would not blame it on
the fig that fell. Okay. Is he also arguing on the case
of the ring of עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? Maybe, maybe not. Maybe
again עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah he'd more be allow you to say
it because there's no way to benefit from it. But at least
by the case of תרומה, Terumah, whatever, he's not going to be
so liberal and he's going to say only by like a big
barrel. רב יוסף אמר אפילו תאנה כנפילתה כך עלייתה, Rav Yosef amar
afilu te'ena kenefilatah kach aliyatah, even a fig, the same way when
it fell into the group, it was only one little fig that
fell into a group, nevertheless it makes the group forbidden. When it
falls out of the group, it's enough to make the group permissible.
Okay. All right. So that's an application of the idea that when
we say, so now what we have is when we say this
whole pile is forbidden, A, do we also apply it to pile
two? Do we apply it to pile three? That's debated. Number and
B, if something falls away and gets destroyed, okay, do are we
allowed to say the thing that got lost, that was the problematic
thing? Now we move on to one other point. Let's see if
we can get to the two dots. Okay. אמר רב אלעזר, Amar
Rav Elazar, said רב אלעזר, Rav Elazar, חבית של תרומה שנפלה בק'
חביות. Chavit shel terumah she-nafla be-kuf chavyot. So you've got, נפלה Nafla
is a funny point. Anyway, you've got one barrel and it's mixed
up in a hundred, they're all תרומה, Terumah, they're all forbidden because
why is it not בטל? Batel? Because it's a sealed barrel. Remember
and the הלכה Halacha is a sealed barrel isn't בטל. Batel.
פותח אחת מהן ונוטל הימנה כדי דמיה ושותה. Pote'ach achat mehen venotel
heimena k'dei dameha veshoteh. So he says here's what you can do.
Open up one barrel. Now as soon as you open up one
barrel, the barrel you just opened is permissible. Why? It's like magic.
Because this barrel that is open, what barrel is not בטל? Batel?
The sealed barrels. As soon as I open it, I don't know
whether this is the one that's אסור Asur or the one that's
permitted. But whatever this is, now that this one, the other ones
are sealed. Now that this one is open, even if this was
the forbidden one, it's בטל, Batel, because it no longer significant, because
it's been opened. You got it? As soon as I open it,
it loses its significance and then the ביטול Bitul applies to this
barrel. So logically I should be able to open it and drink
from it. But that might be like a problem of אין מבטלין
איסור לכתחילה, Ein mevatlin issur l'chatchila, I'm actively doing something that's allowing
ביטול Bitul to take effect. So what he says is, maybe the
way to sort of give lip service to the idea that there's
a ביטול Bitul taking place here, and you know, and there was
some problem, what you do is, if one out of a hundred
barrels is problematic, you remove one-one-hundredth of the wine in the barrel
and you throw it out and you drink the rest. Now that's
of course silly, because in this barrel itself, it's either a hundred
percent okay or a hundred percent not okay, right? But even so,
even though it doesn't make logic, we're sort of saying at least
acknowledge that there's a תערובת Ta'arovat here, imagine that there's a mixture
in the barrel itself, and therefore to recognize the mixture, remove that
percentage of the percentage of this whole, you know, wine room that
has a problematic barrel. If that's one in a hundred or one
in two hundred or whatever it is, remove it and then drink
the rest. Okay. So this is another idea like, oh, the bad
ring was the one that fell in the ocean. Oh, the bad
head was the one that was brought. Okay. Oh, I'm going to
do some fiction, it's not even the same type of fiction, I'm
not blaming it on anything, but I'm going to do something that
at a certain level doesn't make sense, but it'll be a type
of a little ritual and a type of a fiction that'll now
let me drink from this barrel. Okay. Now if you do that,
you're going to be able to... drink from all the barrels because
you just open each one and you remove a little bit from
each one. Now eventually if you do that, you've thrown out a
full barrel's worth, right? And that's maybe the point. I don't want
you to totally get away with something. Okay, each barrel you're going
to do, you're going to remove a hundredth, so if you do
it by all the barrels, you will at least have removed a
barrel's worth from this wine. But if I'm going to be so
strict to say it's not בטל, batel, I'm going to find a
way, this is what's happening here. If you make it so strict,
then there's a counter-pressure to find a way to actually find ways
to make it permissible.
Okay, this is similar to the things we had the other day
with the top layer.
Similar, yeah. Like a certain level of a fiction. Yeah.
This is just one over 101 as opposed to one.
Well, yes, that's true because it's one barrel falling into 100 barrels.
So there's a total of 101. Okay, that's a good point. Okay,
anyway, okay, יתיב רב
דימי וקאמר לה להשמעתא, Yativ Rav Dimi vekame lei lehshmaita, so Rav
Dimi was sitting and saying this over. אמרי רב נחמן, Amrei Rav
Nachman, so Rav Nachman said to him, גמע ושתה? כחזינא הכא, gama
veshasa? kachazeina hacha, what? You're like just swallowing and drinking? I'm seeing
here like how do you get away with this? How are you
לכתחילה l'chatchila allowed to do it?
אלא אימא, Ela eima, that's going too far. נפחצה אחת מהן נוטל
ממנה כדי דמוע ושותה. Niphchatzah achas mehen notel mimena kedei dimu'a veshotah.
Not that you're allowed to open one לכתחילה, l'chatchila,
but if one opened, otherwise it's too much like מבטלין איסור לכתחילה.
mevatlin issur l'chatchila. It's like throwing the ring into the ים המלח.
Yam Hamelach. It's only allowed if one of them fell away. You're
not לכתחילה l'chatchila allowed to do that. That's like אין מבטלין איסור
לכתחילה. ein mevatlin issur l'chatchila. אמר
רבי אושעיא חבית של תרומה שנתערבה במאה וחמשים חביות, Amar Rabbi Oshaya
chavis shel truma shenit'areva beme'ah vachamishim chavi'ot, if one got mixed up
with 150, ונפתחו מאה מהן, veniftachu me'ah mehen, and 100 got opened,
okay, so those 100 are all בטל. batel. נוטל ממנה כדי דמוע
ושותה, Notel mimena kedei dimu'a veshotah, you're able to remove the appropriate
proportion from those 100, ושאר אסורין עד שיפתחו. veshar asurin ad sheyipatechu.
Okay, and the rest remain are forbidden, but if you wind up
if the rest get opened up, they also become permissible if you
go ahead and remove this percentage. Same idea. וחידוש הוא לא אמרינן
איסור ברובא איתא. Vechidush hu lo amrinan issur beruba issa. Just because
100 opened up at one time, we don't say, oh, these 100
can't be בטל batel because the איסור issur one has to remain
in the 100. Okay, we don't say that. We just say that
as soon as something opens, okay, ביטול bitul is going to apply,
even if all 100 got opened, we're going to allow ביטול bitul
to apply. All right, we will end with that.